<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Thomas Kappler&#39;s site. Mostly programming and books. Category &#34;Career.&#34;</title>
  <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Career/" rel="alternate"></link>
  <id>http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Career/</id>
  <updated>2013-07-30T20:45:42+02:00</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Kappler</name>
   <uri>http://www.thomaskappler.net/</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
   <title>&#34;Land the Tech Job You Love&#34; by Andy Lester</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2013-06-05_review_land_the_tech_job_you_love.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2013-06-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2013-06-05:/2013-06-05_review_land_the_tech_job_you_love.html</id>
   <summary type="html">A great resource for job hunting techies, concise and full of valuable advice.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every so often in a hacker&amp;rsquo;s life it&amp;rsquo;s time to get a new job. In my&#xA;own experience, and based on what I hear from peers, this is often a&#xA;pretty painful process. A few issues stand out for me: &amp;ldquo;selling&amp;rdquo;&#xA;yourself instead of being too shy, working your contacts, and thinking&#xA;like the hiring manager.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://petdance.com/&#34;&gt;Andy Lester&lt;/a&gt; has written a concise book of 250&#xA;pages that addresses these issues and many more:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://petdance.com/book/&#34;&gt;Land the Tech Job You Love&lt;/a&gt;. It has been a&#xA;veritable eye-opener for me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Andy has been a software developer and open source hacker for a long&#xA;time, but he has also been hiring technical people for a long time and&#xA;so knows both sides.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The book covers the whole process of a job search from finding open&#xA;positions, preparing your resume and writing a cover letter, to&#xA;interviewing with all its subtleties. It&amp;rsquo;s more than a collection of&#xA;&amp;ldquo;do this, do that&amp;rdquo; lists, though. What impressed me most is the focus&#xA;Andy puts on attitude and on the reasons why you should do this or&#xA;that. He emphasizes shifting your thinking from focusing on yourself&#xA;to focusing on how to help the company you&amp;rsquo;re applying at and their&#xA;hiring manager. This advice guides each step in the job search and&#xA;will put you way ahead of the candidates sending out stock cover&#xA;letters and talking about what &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; want.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying not to gush here, but I find myself hard-pressed to find&#xA;negative points. Naturally, a book like this cannot cover all&#xA;situations you might find yourself in. But it&amp;rsquo;s a great resource to&#xA;get you started and has lots of pointers to additional resources. I&#xA;find myself reaching for this book again and again, also thanks to the&#xA;plentiful examples and concise checklists.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Books"></category>
   <category term="Career"></category>
  </entry>
 </feed>