<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Thomas Kappler&#39;s site. Mostly programming and books. Category &#34;Meetups.&#34;</title>
  <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Meetups/" rel="alternate"></link>
  <id>http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Meetups/</id>
  <updated>2013-07-30T20:39:22+02:00</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Kappler</name>
   <uri>http://www.thomaskappler.net/</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
   <title>Go and five other languages at WebTuesday Zurich</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2013-07-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2013-07-12:/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday.html</id>
   <summary type="html">The last Zurich WebTuesday was fun. Six speakers presented six languages in seven minutes each. I did Go.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past June, fellow Zurich hacker &lt;a href=&#34;http://ivanjovanovic.com/&#34;&gt;Ivan&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;organized a cool &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.webtuesday.ch&#34;&gt;WebTuesday&lt;/a&gt;:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://webtuesday.ch/meetings/20130611/&#34;&gt;seven languages in seven minutes each&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;We ended up with six languages due to a last-minute cancellation, but&#xA;that doesn&amp;rsquo;t detract from the idea: exposing people to different&#xA;programming paradigms, styles, and tool chains in rapid succession to&#xA;expand their horizons and to foster discussion. I think it worked out&#xA;very well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please see &lt;a href=&#34;http://webtuesday.ch/meetings/20130611/&#34;&gt;the announcement&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;for the speaker list and the full program.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All the presentations were great. Thanks to the speakers who put in the&#xA;effort to make them fun!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/static/posts/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday/impression.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For my Go presentation, I made a&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;/static/posts/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday/slides/go-seven-minutes.html&#34;&gt;few simple slides&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;The vintage boxer pic refers to Ivan&amp;rsquo;s characterization of Go that I&#xA;can agree with: somewhat old-fashioned but packing a good punch.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The structure of my presentation is simple. After exposing the&#xA;audience to the syntax with a Hello World, I address concurrency&#xA;through goroutines, channels, and select. Then I give some quick&#xA;examples of how Go makes program design easy with its clever types,&#xA;interfaces and embedded structs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think people liked it and I had some good conversations afterwards.&#xA;The interest in Go as well as other lesser-known languages has&#xA;definitely developed in the Zurich tech scene, and I think we&amp;rsquo;ll see&#xA;interesting stuff in the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
   <category term="Go"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>Riak and Neo4j @zhgeeks</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2013-05-23_riak_and_neo4j_zhgeeks2.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2013-05-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2013-05-23:/2013-05-23_riak_and_neo4j_zhgeeks2.html</id>
   <summary type="html">We had two great zhgeeks meetups recently: Sean Cribbs spoke about Riak and eventual consistency, and Jim Webber presented Neo4j. Sean&#39;s talk was also an intro to distributed systems with a list of foundational papers that I list in this post.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past April we at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/zhgeeks/&#34;&gt;zhgeeks&lt;/a&gt; had&#xA;the opportunity to host two great database-centric meetups.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As an aside, I can now say &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; because&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/al_maisan&#34;&gt;Muharem Hrnjadovic&lt;/a&gt;, founder and&#xA;organizer of zhgeeks, added me as a co-organizer. Make no mistake, I&#xA;didn&amp;rsquo;t do much so far and all credit for zhgeeks goes to Muharem. I&#xA;will get more involved in organizing future meetups, though. We have a&#xA;couple of good ideas, by the way, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jimwebber.org/&#34;&gt;Jim Webber&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Scientist at&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.neotechnology.com/&#34;&gt;Neo Technology&lt;/a&gt;, presented&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/zhgeeks/events/97436192/&#34;&gt;Neo4j and connected data&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;This was a relatively high-level talk where Jim spent the first half&#xA;or so on pointing out use cases for graph databases and the problem&#xA;domains for which they are best suited&amp;mdash;not surprisingly, domains&#xA;with highly interconnected data. Later on Jim showed Neo4J&amp;rsquo;s new query&#xA;language Cypher, which is a very expressive textual query language for&#xA;graphs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/static/posts/2013-05-23_riak_and_neo4j_zhgeeks2/jim webber zhgeeks.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Jim&amp;rsquo;s a great speaker with lots of wit and plenty of humorous slides.&#xA;The audience&amp;mdash;one of the largest we had so far at zhgeeks&amp;mdash;was&#xA;captured.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Jim&amp;rsquo;s presentation we had a brief talk by Florian Müller,&#xA;co-founder of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jooik.com/&#34;&gt;jooik&lt;/a&gt;, about how they use Neo4j in&#xA;their startup. It&amp;rsquo;s always a pleasure to hear of that kind of&#xA;real-world experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Later in April we had &lt;a href=&#34;http://seancribbs.com/&#34;&gt;Sean Cribbs&lt;/a&gt; from&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://basho.com/&#34;&gt;Basho&lt;/a&gt;, makers of the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://basho.com/riak/&#34;&gt;Riak&lt;/a&gt; distributed database, presenting&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/zhgeeks/events/107680222/&#34;&gt;Understanding Eventual Consistency and Riak&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;This was again an awesome talk. Sean wasn&amp;rsquo;t afraid to go into some&#xA;technical details of distributed systems which I appreciated very&#xA;much. He structured the talk as a tour of some of the most influential&#xA;papers in distributed systems, pointing out how Riak implements each&#xA;technique and deals with the trade-offs involved. I found this to be a&#xA;great overview of the field, so I made a list of the papers and&#xA;resources Sean mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sean recommends the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://the-paper-trail.org/blog/&#34;&gt;Paper Trail&lt;/a&gt; blog by Henry&#xA;Robinson that has great write-ups on important topics in&#xA;distributed systems.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fischer, Lynn, Patterson 1985:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cs-www.cs.yale.edu/homes/arvind/cs425/doc/fischer.pdf&#34;&gt;Impossibility of Distributed Consensus with One Faulty Process (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;introduces the &amp;ldquo;FLP impossiblity&amp;rdquo;: in an asynchronous setting&#xA;there is no distributed algorithm that solves the consensus&#xA;problem of several nodes agreeing on a common value. Paper Trail&#xA;has a&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://the-paper-trail.org/blog/a-brief-tour-of-flp-impossibility/&#34;&gt;good post&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;on this paper.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fox, Brewer 1999:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.24.3690&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;Harvest, yield, and scalable tolerant systems (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;focuses on what kind of compromises a distributed system can make&#xA;in case of node failures or partitions. Yield is the probability&#xA;of completing a request and harvest is a measure of the accuracy&#xA;of the response, defined as the fraction of the existing data the&#xA;system used to come up with the response. Coda Hale wrote a great&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://codahale.com/you-cant-sacrifice-partition-tolerance/&#34;&gt;overview article on Harvest, yield and the CAP theorem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Finally, Sean touched on Leslie Lamport&amp;rsquo;s work on safety and&#xA;liveness of distributed systems in his 1977 paper&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.137.9454&#34;&gt;Proving the Correctness of Multiprocess Programs&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;Sean did a great job of relating Lamport&amp;rsquo;s results to currently&#xA;existing algorithms and systems. The basic question is, if you&#xA;have F failures, how many nodes that are still up do you need to&#xA;respond? If you need F + 1 (at least one), it is an eventually&#xA;consistent system. A majority of nodes, 2F + 1, corresponds to&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://research.microsoft.com/users/lamport/pubs/pubs.html#paxos-simple&#34;&gt;Paxos&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;and two-phase-commit. A super majority, 3F + 1, is called&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_fault_tolerance&#34;&gt;Byzantine fault tolerance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Riak itself is heavily based on the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allthingsdistributed.com/files/amazon-dynamo-sosp2007.pdf&#34;&gt;Amazon dynamo paper (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, Sean recommended the talk&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/52414903&#34;&gt;data structures in Riak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A question from the audience was what other solutions in the&#xA;bewildering space of distributed systems and databases were similar to&#xA;Riak. Among the open source ones Sean thought&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.project-voldemort.com/voldemort/&#34;&gt;Voldemort&lt;/a&gt; to be the&#xA;closest, followed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://cassandra.apache.org/&#34;&gt;Cassandra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
   <category term="Databases"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>GDG DevFest Zurich with an intro to Go</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2012-12-10_gdg_devfest_zurich.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2012-12-10:/2012-12-10_gdg_devfest_zurich.html</id>
   <summary type="html">The Google Developers Group Zurich organized a great weekend of talks, hacking and networking in October. Unexpectedly, I got to present Go in an hour-long hands-on tutorial.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before October, I had never made it to a&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gdgzh.ch/&#34;&gt;GDG Zurich&lt;/a&gt; event, but the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/gdgdevfestzurich/&#34;&gt;DevFest 2012&lt;/a&gt; they&#xA;announced sounded too interesting to pass it up. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to bore&#xA;you with the minutiae of how it went down, so let me just say it was a&#xA;great and very well organized weekend. By my rough guess about 100&#xA;hackers showed up, which I found quite impressive. After casual&#xA;introductions and drinks on Friday night we spent Saturday and Sunday&#xA;in the Zurich youth hostel for talks and hacking. Big thanks to the&#xA;organizers Vadim, Michel, Corsin and Robert (see&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/gdgdevfestzurich/home/orga&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), you&#xA;did a great job.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the presentations about AppEngine by Jerome Mouton&#xA;and about the new Google Drive SDK by Nicolas Garnier. Would love to&#xA;play with these at some point.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rest of Saturday was spent chatting and getting to know people,&#xA;until at some point I mentioned working with &lt;a href=&#34;http://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;at &lt;a href=&#34;http://nhumi.com/&#34;&gt;Nhumi&lt;/a&gt; and people got very interested. Almost&#xA;everyone had read about it, but no one had used it. There happened to&#xA;be a free slot left for a codelab on Sunday morning, so I soon found&#xA;myself with a job to do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time I just roughly followed the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tour.golang.org/&#34;&gt;Tour of Go&lt;/a&gt;, skipping ahead a little&#xA;sometimes. This was a good decision as the Go devs have put a lot of&#xA;thought into its structure. In addition, I made just six&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ZOgBTvAoveph4NneI05dV20qn7YUbQeioaEP0D8_4uU/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;slides summarizing some Go essentials from my point of view&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;This was my &amp;ldquo;main points about Go&amp;rdquo; slide:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fun and productive&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Interfaces&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Different &amp;ldquo;OO&amp;rdquo;: embedded structs, methods&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Concurrency&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I gave a code example for each of the latter three points. The&#xA;audience of about 20 seemed to follow along easily and there were&#xA;plenty of questions. It was neat to respond to questions and remarks&#xA;directly by demonstrating things live in the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://play.golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go Playground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thanks everyone for coming, and have fun with Go!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Go"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>Geneva JUG New Year&#39;s meeting 2011</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2011-01-18_geneva_jug_akka_scala.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2011-01-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2011-01-18:/2011-01-18_geneva_jug_akka_scala.html</id>
   <summary type="html">Iulian Dragos on Scala &amp; Jonas Bonér on Akka.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://genevajug.ch/&#34;&gt;Geneva Java User&amp;rsquo;s Group&lt;/a&gt; had their annual&#xA;New Year&amp;rsquo;s meeting yesterday, with two invited speakers. Iulian Dragos&#xA;gave an Intro to Scala, and Jonas Bonér presented his actor library&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://akka.io&#34;&gt;Akka&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Iulian works on Scala and with Scala with Martin Odersky at EPFL&#xA;Lausanne and Odersky&amp;rsquo;s consulting company Scala Solutions. For initial&#xA;motivation, he listed some companies already using Scala in&#xA;production. Apart from the ones known in the anglophone hacker web&#xA;like Twitter and Foursquare, some big European enterprises such as&#xA;Credit Suisse, UBS, and Siemens were on the list. Iulian&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;presentation was then a straightforward intro to Scala. Up to slide&#xA;13, I noted, it was all Perl in a different syntax :-) He then moved&#xA;on to more advanced features such as mix-ins. Their sensitivity to the&#xA;order in which they are included left the audience sceptical. The&#xA;parallel collections of the upcoming Scala 2.9, on the other hand,&#xA;looked great.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Overall a nice intro to Scala. It suffered a bit from lack of&#xA;practical examples for the advanced language features, but that&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;unavoidable given the time constraints. Speaker&amp;rsquo;s note: a laser&#xA;pointer would have been very helpful for going through sample code.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonasboner.com&#34;&gt;Jonas Bonér&lt;/a&gt; is the principal author of Akka,&#xA;a very powerful actor framework written in Scala. Jonas uses Scala&#xA;since 2005. He loves Erlang and only moved on to the JVM world because&#xA;he had difficulties convincing others of its greatness. The natural&#xA;compromise was then to implement an Erlang-style platform using Scala&#xA;actors, which became Akka.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Akka is very optimized. An actor uses only 600 bytes (yes, bytes) of&#xA;memory, so you can spawn millions of them. Syntax is easy and&#xA;flexible: send a message to an actor with a single bang (&lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt;), &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt;&#xA;blocks, &lt;code&gt;!!!&lt;/code&gt; returns a &lt;code&gt;Future&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A unique property of Akka is that it combines actors with Software&#xA;Transactional Memory, usually regarded as two separate ideas to tackle&#xA;concurrency. You write&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;import akka.stm. ...&#xA;&#xA;atomic {&#xA;    atomic {&#xA;        // Atomic blocks are composable, so they don&#39;t break&#xA;        // encapsulation like locks.&#xA;    }&#xA;}&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you, for instance, send a message to an actor a1, which updates its&#xA;state atomically, messages another actor a2, which then also tries to&#xA;updates its state atomically but fails, then the whole chain will be&#xA;rolled back and retried, even if the messaging was&#xA;asynchronous. Powerful indeed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Jonas presented a fascinating integration example towards the end of&#xA;this talk. He likes the Apache Camel integration framework. Akka comes&#xA;with a Camel module. One can define an actor with, for example,&#xA;&lt;code&gt;endpoint &amp;quot;file://foo&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;. Any change to &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; will then be send as a&#xA;message to the actor. The other way round works, too, of course&amp;ndash;think&#xA;websockets.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Almost as an aside, Jonas mentioned that Akka supports code hot-swap&#xA;like Erlang.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Akka looks like a very powerful framework indeed, to be investigated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Jonas presented in a great, buddy-like way, like a fellow hacker&#xA;chatting over a beer. Some ranting and rambling only added to the&#xA;impact of the presentation. His slides were minimal and well&#xA;done&amp;ndash;great talk overall.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
   <category term="Java"></category>
   <category term="Scala"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>Presenting &#34;Practical RDF in Perl&#34; at FrOSCamp Zurich</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2010-09-17-froscamp_zurich.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2010-09-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2010-09-17:/2010-09-17-froscamp_zurich.html</id>
   <summary type="html">Presenting &#34;Practical RDF in Perl&#34;, hanging out at the Perl booth and drinking free-as-in-freedom beer at the Free and Open Source Camp in Zurich, a fun little meeting. Plus a somewhat critical self-review of my talk.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, another one of those belated meeting/event reports: on 2010-09-17,&#xA;I was in Zurich for the first-ever&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.froscamp.org/Welcome&#34;&gt;FrOSCamp&lt;/a&gt;. It was an Open&#xA;Source/Free Software event with an exhibition floor, talks, and &amp;ldquo;a&#xA;fancy party with creative commons licensed beer and music&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;what&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;not to like!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I presented my &amp;ldquo;Praktisches RDF in Perl&amp;rdquo; talk that I recycled from the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jugglingbits.wordpress.com/2010/06/20/semantic-hacking-rdf-in-perl-presentation/&#34;&gt;German Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;to spread the word some more. This time, I had prepared an English&#xA;version, but as I only had German speakers in the audience, I&#xA;presented in German.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately my presentation only drew a handful of people this&#xA;time. Note to self: work on the abstract some more. I had suspected&#xA;that my FrOSCamp one was wordy and not catchy, but didn&amp;rsquo;t get around&#xA;to rewriting it. At least the audience were pretty engaged and asked&#xA;lots of questions, which I prefer to a larger crowd that&amp;rsquo;s half&#xA;asleep.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The presentation was recorded and is now&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.multimedia.ethz.ch/conferences/2010/froscamp/?doi=10.3930/ETHZ/AV-13ff192d-43b9-4628-9ff4-6e4f69f2e01f&#34;&gt;online as slides+audio&lt;/a&gt;. This&#xA;was a first for me. I could forget about it while presenting, but I&#xA;was pretty nervous listening to it for the first time, not sure what&#xA;mess of incoherent rambling and half-finished sentences to&#xA;expect. Fortunately, I found it ok in the end. Of course, I found&#xA;several things to improve, but I guess that&amp;rsquo;s expected for someone who&#xA;doesn&amp;rsquo;t present often and is just getting started. My list of the main&#xA;points to improve is:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The introduction should be much shorter and more focussed. A bit&#xA;like a sales pitch, not as in being obnoxious and fake, but as in&#xA;focussed on getting the audience&amp;rsquo;s attention and appreciation for&#xA;the topic.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Too many sentences didn&amp;rsquo;t flow properly. Simply doing one or two&#xA;more dry runs should fix that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Have some more visualizations such as diagrams on the slides.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I was pleased with a few things about my&#xA;presentation: the style of having little text on the slides and more&#xA;verbal explanation worked well, the code samples seemed to be the&#xA;right size to digest during a talk, and the questions at the end&#xA;showed that people had gotten the key points.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before my presentation, I got to see&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.renee-baecker.de/&#34;&gt;Renee Baecker&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s talk about&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?Perl::Critic&#34;&gt;Perl::Critic&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m using&#xA;it on my code and thus knew the basics, but I appreciated the advanced&#xA;example towards the end, where Renee walked us through writing our own&#xA;critic rules. This works via&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?PPI&#34;&gt;PPI&lt;/a&gt;, so you can find patterns in&#xA;the AST that match the constructs you want to check. I also found it&#xA;interesting to hear Renee&amp;rsquo;s personal experience with the severity&#xA;levels: he&amp;rsquo;s typically on 3, sometimes 2, but 1 is too harsh.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I was mainly hanging out at the Perl booth, a first&#xA;for me! The booth was staffed by Renee and Roman from Winterthur (CH),&#xA;two really nice guys whom I had a great time with, discussing&#xA;everything from Perl modules to freelancing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BTW, remember the blurb from the FrOSCamp website I quoted at the top&#xA;about creative commons licensed beer?&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freebeer.ch/&#34;&gt;That wasn&amp;rsquo;t a joke&lt;/a&gt;. FreeBeer is an organic&#xA;beer, produced by an independent brewery near Zurich, and the recipe&#xA;is online under a CC license. And it tastes great! A cloudy, full&#xA;blonde just how I like it :-)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
   <category term="Perl"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
   <category term="SemanticWeb"></category>
  </entry>
 </feed>