<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Thomas Kappler&#39;s site. Mostly programming and books. Category &#34;Personal Development.&#34;</title>
  <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Personal Development/" rel="alternate"></link>
  <id>http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Personal Development/</id>
  <updated>2013-06-05T17:51:41+02:00</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Kappler</name>
   <uri>http://www.thomaskappler.net/</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
   <title>&#34;Talent is Overrated&#34; by Geoff Colvin</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2011-02-06_review_talent_is_overrated.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2011-02-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2011-02-06:/2011-02-06_review_talent_is_overrated.html</id>
   <summary type="html">Fascinating and important. How top performers really get to be so great. Don&#39;t let a false notion of innate talent stop you.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Geoff Colvin&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Talent-Overrated-Separates-World-Class-Performers/dp/1591842948/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1297014218&amp;amp;sr=8-1&#34;&gt;Talent is Overrated&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;opens with presenting new research findings showing that top&#xA;performers do not have &amp;ldquo;innate gifts&amp;rdquo;. Instead, their achievements are&#xA;the result of lots of &lt;em&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/em&gt;. The author backs this&#xA;claim with different research findings and exemplary biographies, then&#xA;explains the nature of great performance and the kind of practice&#xA;necessary to achieve it, concluding with a chapter on motivation and&#xA;passion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I liked this book so much that I took extensive notes, which you find&#xA;below. Here&amp;rsquo;s the summary: I think it is an important work that might&#xA;change the way you think about personal and professional&#xA;development. From practice design to motivation and passion and the&#xA;nature of great performance, Colvin covers the subject from all angles&#xA;and backs his findings with lots of references.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Talent doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist? Really?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is hard to believe when thinking of such prodigies as Einstein,&#xA;Mozart, or Michael Jordan. Colvin knows this and goes to great lengths&#xA;to present these studies and explain how, in his view, these top&#xA;performers really got to be so good. He walks the reader through the&#xA;childhoods of Mozart and Tiger Woods, and it&amp;rsquo;s indeed surprising what&#xA;we find here: an extreme practice regime starting at two years of age,&#xA;designed by an expert in the field, and tens of thousands of hours of&#xA;practice before both appeared in the public as masters of their&#xA;field. Whether they have/had innate talent or not, their success&#xA;certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t come easily. The author also presents a study showing&#xA;that while chess masters are incredibly good at remembering chess&#xA;boards, this only holds for boards with real, valid&#xA;positions. Presented with boards breaking the rules of chess, they do&#xA;no better than amateurs. Their memory must therefore be the result of&#xA;the years of chess training.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Colvin further points out the incredible progress that has occurred&#xA;across the board in the last hundred years even though our genes&#xA;didn&amp;rsquo;t change in such a short time. A 1908 Olympics record is today&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;top high school level.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Concluding his introduction, Colvin points out what an influence on&#xA;our lives the belief in innate talent has. Parents and teachers direct&#xA;kids to follow a course where they think they might have&#xA;talent. People themselves limit themselves and skip opportunities in&#xA;the belief to lack the necessary talent to go beyond the average.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Deliberate Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So what is this deliberate practice that leads to outstanding results,&#xA;while most people work for years without seeing much improvement? It&#xA;is designed, it can be (and is!) repeated a lot, it allows continuous&#xA;feedback, it is mentally highly demanding, and finally, it is not&#xA;fun&amp;ndash;otherwise, quips Colvin, everyone would do it. If they knew how&#xA;to design such practice, that is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The abovementioned attributes of deliberate practice show that it is&#xA;nothing like the actual work one is practicing for. This explains why&#xA;working in a job even for decades does not necessarily produce&#xA;masters.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is not quite clear whether a top performer can design her own&#xA;practice, or if she needs a coach who is an expert in training design&#xA;and can judge objectively. Tiger Woods, for instance, is still taking&#xA;lessons, while the Comedian Chris Rock designs and practices his&#xA;routines by himself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A pretty incredible story concludes this part of the book. Among the&#xA;first thinking about the design of a training regime to produce&#xA;world-class results was the Hungarian psychologist Laszlo Polgar. He&#xA;went all the way and found, via a newspaper add, a woman willing to&#xA;have children with him to raise in a way carefully designed to make&#xA;them word-class chess players. Surprisingly enough, he found one and&#xA;they had three girls&amp;ndash;all of whom became grand masters after a&#xA;childhood of rigorous training.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Can we pin down a general effect of deliberate practice? What does it&#xA;do that other kinds of practice don&amp;rsquo;t do? For Colvin, it&amp;rsquo;s avoiding&#xA;automaticity. The brain tends to automate repeated activities to save&#xA;mental energy. This automation stops improvement. It also makes one&#xA;vulnerable to distractions because they break the pattern triggering&#xA;the automated routine. Instead, top performers remain conscious of&#xA;their activity throughout their training.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;How deliberate practice works&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For Colvin, &amp;ldquo;perceiving more&amp;rdquo; is the key: more indicators, further&#xA;ahead, with less information. His chess example of the Big Blue&#xA;vs. Kasparov is a little doubtful, I felt he didn&amp;rsquo;t make clear the&#xA;difference in reasoning between the human player thinking in patterns&#xA;and the computer evaluating a large number of positions in advance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Colving also points out here that knowledge plays an important&#xA;role. Experts have more and it&amp;rsquo;s better consolidated. Jeff Immelt,&#xA;then head of GE, launched a study showing that among his managers,&#xA;domain knowledge beat general management knowledge. This is old news&#xA;for developers suffering under non-technical IT management, so it&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;good that a business author like Colvin, who writes for Fortune in his&#xA;day job, points that out. The consolidation of knowledge affects&#xA;memory, too. No one can hold more than nine items in their mind&#xA;simultaneously (for most people it&amp;rsquo;s seven items), but the items can&#xA;be bigger. A chess amateur might remember a single position, while a&#xA;master remembers a whole board.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Applying the principles in our own lives&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The author distinguishes three models of practice depending on the&#xA;kind of task to be practiced.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The music model: You know what you want to convey, like classical&#xA;music is written down, and one needs to convey it effectively. One can&#xA;break the task down into pieces and practice them independently, with&#xA;immediate feedback either by a coach or on video. A good addition is&#xA;to watch top performers and analyze what they are doing well, then&#xA;compare one&amp;rsquo;s own performance to theirs, repeating the process over&#xA;and over.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The chess model, known as the &amp;ldquo;case method&amp;rdquo; in the business world:&#xA;like chess players study individual moves from recorded games, one&#xA;studies lots of example problems. Ideally there is a known, but yet&#xA;hidden, solution, so that after deciding on an action, one can compare&#xA;one&amp;rsquo;s own choice with the known one, like a chess student would study&#xA;a master&amp;rsquo;s game. Of course, for practical problems it&amp;rsquo;s often not&#xA;clear what the solution is, if it even exists&amp;ndash;it helps to discuss&#xA;with coaches and peers in that case.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sports model: Sports is different from classical music in that no&#xA;two situations are ever exactly alike. One practices by working on&#xA;basic conditioning and skill development. Basic conditioning in sports&#xA;is strength and endurance training, and working on cognitive skills,&#xA;math and basic science in intellectual fields of work. Skill&#xA;development means practicing certain situations repeatedly, such as&#xA;sales calls.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having this basic framework for thinking about practice, we need to&#xA;look at the practice itself. Colvin highlights three points that many&#xA;do not follow in their practice. First, there needs to be a clear goal&#xA;of what one wants to achieve, and what steps exactly will be necessary&#xA;to get there. Second, metacognition during training is crucial:&#xA;observing oneself to get a correct assessment of one&amp;rsquo;s mental&#xA;processes. Third, get as much specific feedback as possible and&#xA;analyze it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Innovation and creativity&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The combined impact of the internet and globalization leads to a&#xA;massive commoditization. To thrive in this environment, creativity and&#xA;innovation are key. Can we apply the principles of great performance&#xA;here?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Colvin doesn&amp;rsquo;t believe that creative works are the result of a flash&#xA;of insight. The evidence is conflicting. Colvin presents some&#xA;fascinating work of Dean Keith Simonton, John Hayes (CMU), and Howard&#xA;Gardner (&amp;ldquo;Creative Minds&amp;rdquo;). The summary is that &amp;ldquo;great innovators are&#xA;nourished by knowledge&amp;rdquo;; innovation grows from the past.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Great performance in youth and age&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Colvin first examines what kinds of homes are&#xA;conducive for kids to achieving top performance, then looks into&#xA;maintaining top performance in old age.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter didn&amp;rsquo;t work as well for me as the others. His opening&#xA;teaser of the average age of Nobel prize winners now being six years&#xA;older than 100 years ago seems obvious: as science advances, things&#xA;get more and more complex, requiring more study to understand what&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;been done before.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Colvin&amp;rsquo;s findings on the right kind of environment for children are&#xA;mainly based on Benjamin Bloom&amp;rsquo;s research, and seem plausible, but&#xA;remain too general. The environment must be child-oriented and&#xA;supportive. A strong work ethic based on the goals of excelling and&#xA;spending one&amp;rsquo;s time constructively is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2&gt;Where does the passion come from?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The final chapter addresses the deepest question the book asks: why do&#xA;all that hard practice? Who does it and why, and why don&amp;rsquo;t the others&#xA;do the same?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Colvin first reviews the research on motivation, which agrees that&#xA;intrinsic beats extrinsic motivation by far. But how is intrinsic&#xA;motivation linked to deliberate practice? Possibly through &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;. To&#xA;experience flow, the difficulty level needs to be just&#xA;right. Repeating the same task or practice too often makes it too&#xA;easy, so top performers could be driven to setting the bar higher and&#xA;higher to keep the flow experience.  This I found very insightful and&#xA;exciting, since Csikszentmihalyi&amp;rsquo;s book&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Flow-Psychology-Experience-Mihaly-Csikszentmihalyi/dp/0061339202/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1297013636&amp;amp;sr=8-1&#34;&gt;Flow&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;is next on my reading list.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t explain why people put themselves through the&#xA;grueling practice required for the very top, including lots of&#xA;failure. The author leaves this point open, saying that we simply&#xA;don&amp;rsquo;t understand fully what&amp;rsquo;s behind motivation and passion. He adds&#xA;an interesting observation, though: examining the childhood&#xA;experiences of many top athletes, he found that their passion for&#xA;their sport wasn&amp;rsquo;t there from the start. It only developed after a few&#xA;years of practice, once they started to become really good.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Books"></category>
   <category term="Personal Development"></category>
  </entry>
 </feed>