<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Thomas Kappler&#39;s site. Mostly programming and books. Category &#34;Presenting.&#34;</title>
  <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Presenting/" rel="alternate"></link>
  <id>http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/Presenting/</id>
  <updated>2013-07-30T20:39:22+02:00</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Kappler</name>
   <uri>http://www.thomaskappler.net/</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
   <title>Go and five other languages at WebTuesday Zurich</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2013-07-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2013-07-12:/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday.html</id>
   <summary type="html">The last Zurich WebTuesday was fun. Six speakers presented six languages in seven minutes each. I did Go.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past June, fellow Zurich hacker &lt;a href=&#34;http://ivanjovanovic.com/&#34;&gt;Ivan&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;organized a cool &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.webtuesday.ch&#34;&gt;WebTuesday&lt;/a&gt;:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://webtuesday.ch/meetings/20130611/&#34;&gt;seven languages in seven minutes each&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;We ended up with six languages due to a last-minute cancellation, but&#xA;that doesn&amp;rsquo;t detract from the idea: exposing people to different&#xA;programming paradigms, styles, and tool chains in rapid succession to&#xA;expand their horizons and to foster discussion. I think it worked out&#xA;very well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please see &lt;a href=&#34;http://webtuesday.ch/meetings/20130611/&#34;&gt;the announcement&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;for the speaker list and the full program.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All the presentations were great. Thanks to the speakers who put in the&#xA;effort to make them fun!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/static/posts/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday/impression.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For my Go presentation, I made a&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;/static/posts/2013-07-12_go_and_five_other_languages_at_webtuesday/slides/go-seven-minutes.html&#34;&gt;few simple slides&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;The vintage boxer pic refers to Ivan&amp;rsquo;s characterization of Go that I&#xA;can agree with: somewhat old-fashioned but packing a good punch.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The structure of my presentation is simple. After exposing the&#xA;audience to the syntax with a Hello World, I address concurrency&#xA;through goroutines, channels, and select. Then I give some quick&#xA;examples of how Go makes program design easy with its clever types,&#xA;interfaces and embedded structs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think people liked it and I had some good conversations afterwards.&#xA;The interest in Go as well as other lesser-known languages has&#xA;definitely developed in the Zurich tech scene, and I think we&amp;rsquo;ll see&#xA;interesting stuff in the months to come.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
   <category term="Go"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>GDG DevFest Zurich with an intro to Go</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2012-12-10_gdg_devfest_zurich.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2012-12-10:/2012-12-10_gdg_devfest_zurich.html</id>
   <summary type="html">The Google Developers Group Zurich organized a great weekend of talks, hacking and networking in October. Unexpectedly, I got to present Go in an hour-long hands-on tutorial.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before October, I had never made it to a&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gdgzh.ch/&#34;&gt;GDG Zurich&lt;/a&gt; event, but the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/gdgdevfestzurich/&#34;&gt;DevFest 2012&lt;/a&gt; they&#xA;announced sounded too interesting to pass it up. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to bore&#xA;you with the minutiae of how it went down, so let me just say it was a&#xA;great and very well organized weekend. By my rough guess about 100&#xA;hackers showed up, which I found quite impressive. After casual&#xA;introductions and drinks on Friday night we spent Saturday and Sunday&#xA;in the Zurich youth hostel for talks and hacking. Big thanks to the&#xA;organizers Vadim, Michel, Corsin and Robert (see&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/gdgdevfestzurich/home/orga&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), you&#xA;did a great job.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the presentations about AppEngine by Jerome Mouton&#xA;and about the new Google Drive SDK by Nicolas Garnier. Would love to&#xA;play with these at some point.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rest of Saturday was spent chatting and getting to know people,&#xA;until at some point I mentioned working with &lt;a href=&#34;http://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;at &lt;a href=&#34;http://nhumi.com/&#34;&gt;Nhumi&lt;/a&gt; and people got very interested. Almost&#xA;everyone had read about it, but no one had used it. There happened to&#xA;be a free slot left for a codelab on Sunday morning, so I soon found&#xA;myself with a job to do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time I just roughly followed the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tour.golang.org/&#34;&gt;Tour of Go&lt;/a&gt;, skipping ahead a little&#xA;sometimes. This was a good decision as the Go devs have put a lot of&#xA;thought into its structure. In addition, I made just six&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ZOgBTvAoveph4NneI05dV20qn7YUbQeioaEP0D8_4uU/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;slides summarizing some Go essentials from my point of view&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;This was my &amp;ldquo;main points about Go&amp;rdquo; slide:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fun and productive&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Interfaces&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Different &amp;ldquo;OO&amp;rdquo;: embedded structs, methods&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Concurrency&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I gave a code example for each of the latter three points. The&#xA;audience of about 20 seemed to follow along easily and there were&#xA;plenty of questions. It was neat to respond to questions and remarks&#xA;directly by demonstrating things live in the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://play.golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go Playground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thanks everyone for coming, and have fun with Go!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Go"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>&#34;Confessions of a Public Speaker&#34; by Scott Berkun</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2011-03-20_review_confessions_of_a_public_speaker.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2011-03-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2011-03-20:/2011-03-20_review_confessions_of_a_public_speaker.html</id>
   <summary type="html">Excellent. A must-read if you want to improve your public speaking.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scott Berkun is a former software engineer who changed his career to&#xA;being an author and public speaker. This is an interesting career&#xA;path, and in this book Berkun tells the story of how he got into&#xA;public speaking and what he picked up on the long road of mastering&#xA;this skill.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scottberkun.com/books/the-book-confessions-of-a-public-speaker/&#34;&gt;Confessions&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;is a book on public speaking, but not in a reference or text book kind&#xA;of way. In the author&amp;rsquo;s own words, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;highly personal and&#xA;opinionated&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Berkun mostly builds the chapters around personal stories,&#xA;experiences&amp;mdash;good and bad&amp;mdash;he had when speaking, and the lessons&#xA;learned from these experiences. While there are also plenty of&#xA;literature references to back up some claims, the meat of the book is&#xA;in this personal approach. And indeed, after reading this book one&#xA;gets the impression that this approach is essential, because in the&#xA;end successful public speaking is measured by the degree to which the&#xA;speaker emotionally captures the audience. Beyond listing tricks and&#xA;guidelines to slide design, although he touches on these subjects,&#xA;Berkun focuses on capturing the audience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Below you&amp;rsquo;ll find notes and brief summaries I made for most of the&#xA;chapters. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the subject or if you simply need to&#xA;present once in a while, I strongly recommend reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;I Can&amp;rsquo;t See You Naked&lt;/em&gt;, Berkun starts off with a chapter to put&#xA;you at ease: no one cares as much as you do when things go&#xA;wrong. People care and remember when it went right. It&amp;rsquo;s a long&#xA;learning process to become good at presenting, and Berkun remarks &amp;ldquo;if&#xA;you&amp;rsquo;d like to be good at something, the first thing to go out the&#xA;window is the notion of perfection&amp;rdquo;. Perfection stops you from&#xA;learning and taking chances. Be yourself and be useful, with the&#xA;mistakes you make.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Attack Of The Butterflies&lt;/em&gt; deals with being afraid of the&#xA;stage. Being nervous when facing a crowd is built in to humans through&#xA;evolution and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing you can do about that.  But fear is also&#xA;good because it focuses attention. All interesting things in life come&#xA;with fears: asking the cute girl for a date, applying for a job,&#xA;writing a novel.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So what to do to make that fear manageable and even useful? Practice a&#xA;lot. By actually standing up and imagining a crowd and&#xA;presenting. Apart from improving the presentation, it makes you&#xA;comfortable and alerts to potential problems. Also, on the day of the&#xA;talk, arrive early and get accustomed to the room and the tech.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The chapter &lt;em&gt;$30,000 An Hour&lt;/em&gt; explains the lecture circuit and the&#xA;economics of public speaking. Since it&amp;rsquo;s not a goal of mine to earn&#xA;money by speaking, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t that relevant to me, but has some&#xA;interesting information. There&amp;rsquo;s a list of exemplary fees for a&#xA;one-hour lecture, topped by Bill Clinton at $150,000+.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To Work A Tough Room&lt;/em&gt; is actually about the room! Berkun says its&#xA;importance is vastly underestimated and calls for more real theaters.&#xA;He presents his density theory: that not the absolute size of the&#xA;crowd matters, but its density. Facing a mostly empty room, do what&#xA;you can to make them come forward. Offer rewards!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do Not Eat The Microphone&lt;/em&gt; is titled after the expression meaning the&#xA;moment when the audience&amp;rsquo;s confidence in having its needs met is lost,&#xA;and people stop listening. How to avoid that? Berkun says, besides&#xA;following the more technical basics of good presentations, the key is&#xA;in thinking your talk through thoroughly. &amp;ldquo;All good public speaking is&#xA;based on good private thinking&amp;rdquo;. Berkun fights the myth of spontaneous&#xA;inspiration&amp;ndash;good public speeches are the product of lots of work and&#xA;practice.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of course you also need to get your deep thoughts across. Prepare&#xA;doing four things: 1. take a strong position in the title, 2. think&#xA;carefully about your audience, 3. make your points as concise as&#xA;possible, and 4. know likely counterarguments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Science Of Not Boring People&lt;/em&gt; goes deeper into some techniques to&#xA;ensure keeping the audience with you. This highly useful chapter&#xA;covers pacing and rhythm, story telling, involving the audience, and&#xA;other subjects.  .&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At some point you&amp;rsquo;ll have given a few presentations, and like in every&#xA;other field,&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;/2011-02-06_review_talent_is_overrated.html&#34;&gt;feedback is the key to improve&lt;/a&gt;. Berkun gives tips on what questions to ask&#xA;your audience as well as on practicing by yourself at home.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Clutch Is Your Friend&lt;/em&gt; gives extra advice for lectures where the&#xA;goal is to actually teach the audience something, as opposed to, for&#xA;instance, merely giving an overview of a topic or a motivational&#xA;speech. The alternate title is &amp;ldquo;Why Teaching Is Almost Impossible&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;in&#xA;Berkun&amp;rsquo;s view, given the difficulties in teaching a large group of&#xA;people effectively, you can only prepare and follow a few simple rules&#xA;and hope for the best. The rules: small numbers win, make it active&#xA;and interesting, and start with an insight that interests the&#xA;students.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With &lt;em&gt;Confessions&lt;/em&gt;, a great and funny chapter ends the book: Berkun&#xA;confesses some tricks he uses and some thoughts going through his mind&#xA;frequently when speaking. You learn that everything is allowed as long&#xA;as you capture your audience, and after all, &amp;ldquo;the easiest way to be&#xA;interesting is to be honest&amp;rdquo;. If you want to know if Berkun wears&#xA;underwear when giving a talk, read this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The book has several useful appendices with concise extra information,&#xA;such as How To Make A Point. Also, the references are great. To keep&#xA;in mind: Donald A. Bligh, &lt;em&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the Use of Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, and Ken Bain,&#xA;&lt;em&gt;What the Best College Teachers Do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As I said before, a great book, recommended without hesitation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Books"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <title>Presenting &#34;Practical RDF in Perl&#34; at FrOSCamp Zurich</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2010-09-17-froscamp_zurich.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2010-09-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2010-09-17:/2010-09-17-froscamp_zurich.html</id>
   <summary type="html">Presenting &#34;Practical RDF in Perl&#34;, hanging out at the Perl booth and drinking free-as-in-freedom beer at the Free and Open Source Camp in Zurich, a fun little meeting. Plus a somewhat critical self-review of my talk.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, another one of those belated meeting/event reports: on 2010-09-17,&#xA;I was in Zurich for the first-ever&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.froscamp.org/Welcome&#34;&gt;FrOSCamp&lt;/a&gt;. It was an Open&#xA;Source/Free Software event with an exhibition floor, talks, and &amp;ldquo;a&#xA;fancy party with creative commons licensed beer and music&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;what&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;not to like!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I presented my &amp;ldquo;Praktisches RDF in Perl&amp;rdquo; talk that I recycled from the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jugglingbits.wordpress.com/2010/06/20/semantic-hacking-rdf-in-perl-presentation/&#34;&gt;German Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;to spread the word some more. This time, I had prepared an English&#xA;version, but as I only had German speakers in the audience, I&#xA;presented in German.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately my presentation only drew a handful of people this&#xA;time. Note to self: work on the abstract some more. I had suspected&#xA;that my FrOSCamp one was wordy and not catchy, but didn&amp;rsquo;t get around&#xA;to rewriting it. At least the audience were pretty engaged and asked&#xA;lots of questions, which I prefer to a larger crowd that&amp;rsquo;s half&#xA;asleep.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The presentation was recorded and is now&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.multimedia.ethz.ch/conferences/2010/froscamp/?doi=10.3930/ETHZ/AV-13ff192d-43b9-4628-9ff4-6e4f69f2e01f&#34;&gt;online as slides+audio&lt;/a&gt;. This&#xA;was a first for me. I could forget about it while presenting, but I&#xA;was pretty nervous listening to it for the first time, not sure what&#xA;mess of incoherent rambling and half-finished sentences to&#xA;expect. Fortunately, I found it ok in the end. Of course, I found&#xA;several things to improve, but I guess that&amp;rsquo;s expected for someone who&#xA;doesn&amp;rsquo;t present often and is just getting started. My list of the main&#xA;points to improve is:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The introduction should be much shorter and more focussed. A bit&#xA;like a sales pitch, not as in being obnoxious and fake, but as in&#xA;focussed on getting the audience&amp;rsquo;s attention and appreciation for&#xA;the topic.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Too many sentences didn&amp;rsquo;t flow properly. Simply doing one or two&#xA;more dry runs should fix that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Have some more visualizations such as diagrams on the slides.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I was pleased with a few things about my&#xA;presentation: the style of having little text on the slides and more&#xA;verbal explanation worked well, the code samples seemed to be the&#xA;right size to digest during a talk, and the questions at the end&#xA;showed that people had gotten the key points.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before my presentation, I got to see&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.renee-baecker.de/&#34;&gt;Renee Baecker&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s talk about&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?Perl::Critic&#34;&gt;Perl::Critic&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m using&#xA;it on my code and thus knew the basics, but I appreciated the advanced&#xA;example towards the end, where Renee walked us through writing our own&#xA;critic rules. This works via&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?PPI&#34;&gt;PPI&lt;/a&gt;, so you can find patterns in&#xA;the AST that match the constructs you want to check. I also found it&#xA;interesting to hear Renee&amp;rsquo;s personal experience with the severity&#xA;levels: he&amp;rsquo;s typically on 3, sometimes 2, but 1 is too harsh.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I was mainly hanging out at the Perl booth, a first&#xA;for me! The booth was staffed by Renee and Roman from Winterthur (CH),&#xA;two really nice guys whom I had a great time with, discussing&#xA;everything from Perl modules to freelancing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BTW, remember the blurb from the FrOSCamp website I quoted at the top&#xA;about creative commons licensed beer?&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freebeer.ch/&#34;&gt;That wasn&amp;rsquo;t a joke&lt;/a&gt;. FreeBeer is an organic&#xA;beer, produced by an independent brewery near Zurich, and the recipe&#xA;is online under a CC license. And it tastes great! A cloudy, full&#xA;blonde just how I like it :-)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Meetups"></category>
   <category term="Perl"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
   <category term="SemanticWeb"></category>
  </entry>
 </feed>