<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Thomas Kappler&#39;s site. Mostly programming and books. Category &#34;SemanticWeb.&#34;</title>
  <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/SemanticWeb/" rel="alternate"></link>
  <id>http://www.thomaskappler.net/categories/SemanticWeb/</id>
  <updated>2013-05-09T12:52:16+02:00</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Kappler</name>
   <uri>http://www.thomaskappler.net/</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
   <title>Presenting &#34;Practical RDF in Perl&#34; at FrOSCamp Zurich</title>
   <link href="http://www.thomaskappler.net/2010-09-17-froscamp_zurich.html" rel="alternate"></link>
   <updated>2010-09-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>tag:www.thomaskappler.net,2010-09-17:/2010-09-17-froscamp_zurich.html</id>
   <summary type="html">Presenting &#34;Practical RDF in Perl&#34;, hanging out at the Perl booth and drinking free-as-in-freedom beer at the Free and Open Source Camp in Zurich, a fun little meeting. Plus a somewhat critical self-review of my talk.</summary>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, another one of those belated meeting/event reports: on 2010-09-17,&#xA;I was in Zurich for the first-ever&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.froscamp.org/Welcome&#34;&gt;FrOSCamp&lt;/a&gt;. It was an Open&#xA;Source/Free Software event with an exhibition floor, talks, and &amp;ldquo;a&#xA;fancy party with creative commons licensed beer and music&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;what&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;not to like!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I presented my &amp;ldquo;Praktisches RDF in Perl&amp;rdquo; talk that I recycled from the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jugglingbits.wordpress.com/2010/06/20/semantic-hacking-rdf-in-perl-presentation/&#34;&gt;German Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;to spread the word some more. This time, I had prepared an English&#xA;version, but as I only had German speakers in the audience, I&#xA;presented in German.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately my presentation only drew a handful of people this&#xA;time. Note to self: work on the abstract some more. I had suspected&#xA;that my FrOSCamp one was wordy and not catchy, but didn&amp;rsquo;t get around&#xA;to rewriting it. At least the audience were pretty engaged and asked&#xA;lots of questions, which I prefer to a larger crowd that&amp;rsquo;s half&#xA;asleep.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The presentation was recorded and is now&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.multimedia.ethz.ch/conferences/2010/froscamp/?doi=10.3930/ETHZ/AV-13ff192d-43b9-4628-9ff4-6e4f69f2e01f&#34;&gt;online as slides+audio&lt;/a&gt;. This&#xA;was a first for me. I could forget about it while presenting, but I&#xA;was pretty nervous listening to it for the first time, not sure what&#xA;mess of incoherent rambling and half-finished sentences to&#xA;expect. Fortunately, I found it ok in the end. Of course, I found&#xA;several things to improve, but I guess that&amp;rsquo;s expected for someone who&#xA;doesn&amp;rsquo;t present often and is just getting started. My list of the main&#xA;points to improve is:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The introduction should be much shorter and more focussed. A bit&#xA;like a sales pitch, not as in being obnoxious and fake, but as in&#xA;focussed on getting the audience&amp;rsquo;s attention and appreciation for&#xA;the topic.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Too many sentences didn&amp;rsquo;t flow properly. Simply doing one or two&#xA;more dry runs should fix that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Have some more visualizations such as diagrams on the slides.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I was pleased with a few things about my&#xA;presentation: the style of having little text on the slides and more&#xA;verbal explanation worked well, the code samples seemed to be the&#xA;right size to digest during a talk, and the questions at the end&#xA;showed that people had gotten the key points.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before my presentation, I got to see&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.renee-baecker.de/&#34;&gt;Renee Baecker&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s talk about&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?Perl::Critic&#34;&gt;Perl::Critic&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m using&#xA;it on my code and thus knew the basics, but I appreciated the advanced&#xA;example towards the end, where Renee walked us through writing our own&#xA;critic rules. This works via&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/perldoc?PPI&#34;&gt;PPI&lt;/a&gt;, so you can find patterns in&#xA;the AST that match the constructs you want to check. I also found it&#xA;interesting to hear Renee&amp;rsquo;s personal experience with the severity&#xA;levels: he&amp;rsquo;s typically on 3, sometimes 2, but 1 is too harsh.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I was mainly hanging out at the Perl booth, a first&#xA;for me! The booth was staffed by Renee and Roman from Winterthur (CH),&#xA;two really nice guys whom I had a great time with, discussing&#xA;everything from Perl modules to freelancing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BTW, remember the blurb from the FrOSCamp website I quoted at the top&#xA;about creative commons licensed beer?&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freebeer.ch/&#34;&gt;That wasn&amp;rsquo;t a joke&lt;/a&gt;. FreeBeer is an organic&#xA;beer, produced by an independent brewery near Zurich, and the recipe&#xA;is online under a CC license. And it tastes great! A cloudy, full&#xA;blonde just how I like it :-)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</content>
   <category term="Perl"></category>
   <category term="Presenting"></category>
   <category term="SemanticWeb"></category>
  </entry>
 </feed>